Guide to the Century of Progress International Exposition - New York World's Fair Collection
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Century of Progress International Exposition - New York World's Fair collection
1931-1940
MS 820
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
41
The collection includes printed matter and publicity material related to the Century of Progress International Exposition in Chicago (1933-1934) and the New York World's Fair (1939-1940), including such miscellaneous administrative records of the New York World's Fair as the annual report for 1938 and organizational charts. A main strength of the collection is the printed material from more than one thousand exhibitors at both fairs, comprising business, non-profit institutions, and governments. The manufacturers' catalogues in many cases offer lists of specifications and illustrations of both capital and consumer goods, which also provide a broad sampling of advertising and design of the period.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
These items were brought together by Yale Librarian Sherman Kent, who solicited most of them from the exhibitors. Much of the administrative material for the New York World's Fair was contributed by its Director of Research, Frank Monaghan, also an assistant professor of history at Yale.
Arrangement
Arranged in two series: I. Century of Progress. II. New York World's Fair.
Scope and Contents
The Century of Progress International Exposition - New York World's Fair Collection consists of forty-one linear feet of printed matter and publicity material related to the exhibits at the Century of Progress International Exposition in Chicago (1933-1934) and the New York World's Fair (1939-1940). These items were brought together by Yale Librarian Sherman Kent, who solicited most of them by mail from the exhibitors. He received not only material prepared for distribution at the fairs, but also other current publications, some of which were not available to visitors at the exhibits. From the fair administrations he obtained guidebooks, newspapers, press releases, photographs, and other publicity and administrative material. Much of the administrative material for the New York World's Fair was contributed by its Director of Research, Frank Monaghan, who was also an assistant professor of history at Yale.
Many exhibitors do not appear in the collection because they did not respond to the Library's request or did not have anything to send, but the thousand or more exhibitors who are included are broadly representative of the two expositions. Most belong to one of three categories: businesses, non-profit institutions, and governments. Among the businesses are such major corporations as General Motors and Republic Steel and such smaller firms as the Coatesville Plate Washer Company and American Bird Products, Inc. The non-profit institutions include schools (Tri-State College), charities (The American Committee for the Control of Rheumatism), and churches (the Seventh-Day Adventists). Among the governments are those of American states and of many countries in Europe and Latin America, although the beginning of the Second World War led to the cancellation of some foreign exhibits in 1940. There is a separate series for each exposition, and each series is arranged alphabetically by exhibitor.
The contents of the exhibitors' publications can be summarized under three headings: explanation of the exhibit; description of the exhibitor's product or service; and general information related to the product or service. The nature of the material in the first category is self-evident. The second category has some items prepared for distribution at the fairs but consists mainly of catalogs and brochures intended for general use in public or customer relations. The third category is exemplified by a booklet, Cleanliness through the Ages, offered by the Cudahy Packing Company, distributor of Old Dutch Cleanser.
This collection is a valuable source of information about the expositions, the exhibits, and the ordinary activities of individual exhibitors. Especially important from the latter point of view are the catalogs and brochures of manufacturers, which provide lists, specifications, and illustrations of such capital and consumer goods as industrial machinery, automobiles, and furniture. The representation of activities other than manufacturing is less comprehensive but still useful. Researchers seeking specific information about exhibits or exhibitors will find it helpful to consult the index boxed at the beginning of each series, which lists both exhibitors and their major products.
The collection is also an important resource for the study of American society and, culture in the 1930s, whether the historian chooses to address the subject directly or to use either fair to epitomize certain themes. The Century of Progress International Exposition and the New York World's Fair were showcases for American institutions, and the publications in this collection offer massive evidence of their ideas about their nation and their time. Historians undertaking this kind of study may want to orient themselves by examining the guidebooks and other general material boxed at the beginning of each series or by consulting the Chicago Tribune and the New York Times on microfilm.
Advertising; Exhibitions; Industrial arts; Manufactures; Popular culture; Technology; Middle West; New York (State); Century of Progress International Exposition ( 1933-1934 Chicago, Ill.); New York World's Fair ( 1939-1940 New York, N.Y.)
- CENTURY OF PROGRESS INTERNATIONAL EXPOSITION, 1931-1934; Series I; 17 linear feet (37 Boxes)
  Scope and Contents
  Boxes 1 and lA contain an index to the exhibitors represented in this series with some cross-references from product to exhibitor. It is not guaranteed to be entirely accurate or complete.
  Boxes 2-4 contain general publications and miscellaneous publicity and administrative material.
  Boxes 4-34 contain publications, printed novelty items, and photographs related to individual exhibits. The arrangement is alphabetical by exhibitor.
  Boxes 35 and 35A contain oversize publications related to individual exhibits.
  - Index
    - A - National R (Box 1)
    - National S - Z (Box 1A)
  - Reference works used in preparing the collection (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - J.K. Wilcox: "Checklist of the Official Publications of the Century of Progress International Exposition and its Exhibitors, 1933," John Crerar Library, Reference List no. 27, Chicago, 1933 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Harold H. Laskey: lists of publications about Chicago and the Century of Progress, 1933-1934 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - General official publications (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Programs for days in honor of foreign countries (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Pamphlets for special exhibitions (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Hall of Science publications (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Official photographs (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Miscellaneous correspondence (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Lists of exhibitors and concessionaires (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Press releases (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Progress (the exposition newsletter), 1931 Apr 1 - Dec 30 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Progress, 1932 Jan 6 - Dec 28 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Progress, 1933 Jan 4 - 1934 May 15 (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - World's Fair Clip Sheet (for use by newspaper editors), 1934 Mar 12 - Oct 8 (Box 4, Folder 15)
  - Exhibitors
    - Ab - American D (Box 4)
    - American E - As (Box 5)
    - At - Bo (Box 6)
    - Br - Can (Box 7)
    - Cap - Chicago Te (Box 8)
    - Chicago Tu - Col (Box 9)
    - Com - Cz (Box 10)
    - Da - Diebold (Box 11)
    - Diebold - Do (Box 12)
    - Du - El (Box 13)
    - En - Fre (Box 14)
    - Fri - General E (Box 15)
    - General F - Ham (Box 16)
    - Har - Hz (Box 17)
    - Il - Ir (Box 18)
    - Is - Ker (Box 19)
    - Kew - Lif (Box 20)
    - Lig - Ma (Box 21)
    - Mc - National C (Box 22)
    - National D - Nz (Box 23)
    - Oa - Oz (Box 24)
    - Pa - Pf (Box 25)
    - Ph - Ren (Box 26)
    - Rep - Sea (Box 27)
    - Sen - Sta (Box 28)
    - Ste - Tra (Box 29)
    - Tri - United States C (Box 30)
    - United States D - United States M (Box 31)
    - United States P - Wau (Box 32)
    - Way - Wilb (Box 33)
    - Will - Z (Box 34)
    - Oversize (Box 35)
    - Oversize (Box 35A)
- NEW YORK WORLD'S FAIR, 1938-1940; Series II; 24 linear feet (54 Boxes)
  Boxes 36A-D contain an index to the exhibitors represented in this series with some cross-references from product to exhibitor. They are not guaranteed to be entirely accurate or complete.
  Boxes 36-40 contain general publications and miscellaneous publicity and administrative material.
  Boxes 40-86 contain publications, printed novelty items, and photographs related to individual exhibits. The arrangement is alphabetical by exhibitor except that Boxes 83-86 contain miscellaneous and oversize items.
  - Index cards
    - A - He (Box 36A)
    - Ho - Pa (Box 36B)
    - Ph - Za (Box 36C)
    - Information manual (Box 36D)
  - Information Manual (two editions), 1939 (Box 37, Folder 1)
  - Official Guide Book (three editions), 1939 (Box 37, Folder 2)
  - News Release, 1938 January 2 - 1939 February 5, undated (Box 37, Folder 3)
  - World of Tomorrow, 1938 December 1 - 1939 January 19 (Box 38, Folder 4)
  - Today at the Fair, 1939 April 30 - May 18 (Box 38, Folder 5)
  - Information Bulletin, 1939 (Box 38, Folder 6)
  - Press releases of the Department of Feature Publicity, 1939 (Box 38, Folder 7)
  - Fair Almanac, 1939 (Box 38, Folder 8)
  - Calendar of special days and events, 1939 (Box 38, Folder 8)
  - Teaching the New York World's Fair, no. 1-4, 1939 (Box 38, Folder 9)
  - Teaching the New York World's Fair, no. 1-6, 1940 (Box 38, Folder 9)
  - World's Fair Daily, 1940 June 8-17 (Box 38, Folder 10)
  - Bulletins of the Department of Public Education, no. 1-16B, 1940 (Box 38, Folder 11)
  - Miscellaneous publications, 1939-1940 (Box 38, Folder 12-13)
  - Fun at the Fair: A Trip to the New York World's Fair of 1940 with Bobby and Betty (Box 38, Folder 14)
  - Mayor's Official World's Fair Rooming Bureau, Inc.: leaflet, 1940 (Box 38, Folder 15)
  - Maps, 1938-1940, undated (Box 38, Folder 16)
  - Invitations, programs, and menus, 1939 (Box 39, Folder 17)
  - Photographs, n.d. (Box 39, Folder 18)
  - Publications on art exhibits, 1939-1940 (Box 39, Folder 19)
  - Lists of murals and sculptures, 1939, undated (Box 39, Folder 20)
  - Miscellaneous publicity material, 1938-1939 (Box 39, Folder 21)
  - Miscellaneous papers related to the re-enactment of Washington's inaugural journey, 1939 (Box 39, Folder 22)
  - Annual Report, 1938 (Box 39, Folder 23)
  - Third Attendance Survey, 1939 November 13 (Box 39, Folder 24)
  - Staff directories, 1939, undated (Box 39, Folder 25)
  - Organizational charts, 1939 (Box 39, Folder 26)
  - Lists of personnel, 1939, undated (Box 39, Folder 26)
  - Lists of chairmen of advisory committees, 1939, undated (Box 40, Folder 27)
  - Sherman Kent: form letters to exhibitors, 1939-1940 (Box 40, Folder 28)
  - Exhibitors
    - Ac - American Bi (Box 40)
    - American Br - American Te (Box 41)
    - American To - Bab (Box 42)
    - Bak - Bel (Box 43)
    - Bet - Brazil (Box 44)
    - Brazil - British Pavilion (Box 45)
    - British Pavilion (Box 46)
    - British Pavilion - Buf (Box 47)
    - Bur - Cad (Box 48)
    - Canada (Box 49)
    - Car - Coa (Box 50)
    - Con - Cz (Box 51)
    - Da - Del (Box 52)
    - Den - Douglas Fir (Box 53)
    - Douglas Fir - Electric Utilities (Box 54)
    - Electric Utilities - Fer (Box 55)
    - Fin - Florida (Box 56)
    - Florida - Franc (Box 57)
    - Frank - General F (Box 58)
    - General M - Gla (Box 59)
    - Gle - Hoo (Box 60)
    - Hou - International B (Box 61)
    - International C - Ireland (Box 62)
    - Ireland - Italy (Box 63)
    - Ja - Lak (Box 64)
    - Lan - Lin (Box 65)
    - Lon - Mes (Box 66)
    - Met - National Al (Box 67)
    - National Au - Nev (Box 68)
    - New D - New York Air Brake (Box 69)
    - New York Air Brake - New York T (Box 70)
    - New York Z - Owens-Corning (Box 71)
    - Owens-Corning - Pi (Box 72)
    - Pl - Rad (Box 73)
    - Rai - Rz (Box 74)
    - Sa - Sh (Box 75)
    - Si - Su (Box 76)
    - Sw - Tam (Box 77)
    - Tay - Turk (Box 78)
    - Turn - Val (Box 79)
    - Van - West (Box 80)
    - Western - Wheeling Steel (Box 81)
    - Wheeling Steel - Yugoslavia (Box 82)
    - Yugoslavia - Z, Miscellaneous (Box 83)
    - Oversize (Box 84)
    - Oversize (Box 85)
    - Oversize (Box 86)